

home: djps.github.io github: djps linkedin: sindendavid twitter: @david_sinden david.sinden@gmail.com

Innovative applied mathematician with a strong track record in scientific computation, with over 15 years' experience working in applied research with a focus on medical interventions, internationally recognised expert on ultrasound simulation for therapy and diagnosis. Looking for new challenges in modelling to support medical device development, open to relocation.

- Formulates realistic yet tractable mathematical models, and deployable, tested and documented simulations. Excellent coding and software development skills developed through clinical/commercial deployment, satisfying ISO 13485/IEC 62304 standards.
- Communication skills refined through working in multi-disciplinary, international teams at the interface of academic research and industry; lecturing and teaching at universities; delivering invited presentations at international conferences.
- 17 peer-reviewed journal papers (over 250 citations), a book chapter, acquisition of grants (over 500,000€), 12 invited presentations, industrial supervisor to three PhD students, an MSc student, and maintainer of widely used open source code, k-wave-python

Experience

2019- Fraunhofer Institute for Digital Medicine MEVIS

Bremen, Germany

Senior Research Scientist - Modelling and Simulation Group

Skills: python, VTK, ultrasound modelling, treatment planning, software development

- Developed large-scale simulations for microwave and ultrasound ablative therapies by architecting and parallelizing high-performance numerical methods, enabling clinically relevant treatment planning at scale.
- Engineered fast ultrasound beamforming algorithms and a transcranial acoustic/elastic propagation simulator by leveraging GPU-accelerated reconstruction techniques, delivering novel application.

2014–2019 National Physical Laboratory

Teddington, United Kingdom

Senior Research Scientist - Medical Ultrasound Group

Skills: python, VTK, ultrasound modelling, treatment planning, software development

• Established measurement-based simulation for nonlinear propagation through complex media by integrating empirical measurements into computational models, incorporated into IEC technical specification 63587.

2011-2014 Institute of Cancer Research/The Royal Marsden Hospital

Sutton, United Kingdom

Post-Doctoral Research Associate - Therapeutic Ultrasound Group/Joint Department of Physics

Skills: python, VTK, ultrasound modelling, treatment planning, software development

• Developed an ultrasound-guided high-intensity focused ultrasound treatment planning system with a multi-element phased-array by integrating beamforming control, for focal steering and enhanced safety.

2008–2011 University College London

London, United Kingdom

Post-Doctoral Research Associate - Ultrasonics Group/Department of Mechanical Engineering Skills: python, VTK, ultrasound modelling, treatment planning, software development

• Investigated the influence of cavitation on therapeutic ultrasound by employing numerical and analytical approaches, enabling accurate prediction of cavitation in order to optimize treatment efficacy and safety.

Education

2000-2003

9.2004-6.2008 **PhD - Dynamical Systems**

University College London, UK University of Bath, UK

2003-2004 MSc - Modern Applications of Mathematics

Offiver sity of

BSc - Mathematics with Applied Mathematics/Mathematical Physics

Imperial College London, UK

Awards & Esteem Indicators

2020 IEEE IUS Challenge on Ultrasound Beamforming with Deep Learning (CUBDL)

Joint first place in international machine learning challenge applied to ultrasound image reconstruction (2020)

2015- International Expert

Member IEC/BSI Technical Committee 87 (Ultrasonics), in an individual capacity, associate IMA, full member IOP

Various Enhanced Scholarships

Enhanced funding for MSc (2004), PhD (2008) and post-doctoral work (2014) from UK funding agency EPSRC

Skills

Programming: python, C++, Matlab, OpenCL

DevOps: git, svn, github, gitlab, google test, pytest, make, cmake, visual studio **Computation:** FEniCS, Comsol

Languages: English (native), German (B2.1) with permanent residency

Libraries: ITK, VTK, boost, eigen